a question for Gil have you ever used
HCG in addition to the trt and if so
what is your experience with
it oh absolutely we do this as an
adjunct all the time with guys but again
not with everyone not everyone needs it
not everyone will benefit from it so
first we have to understand what HCG is
excuse me I believe the person asking
the question probably understands it to
a degree but for those who don't I just
want to give like a very brief
explanation so HCG
stands for human chanic anatropin fancy
word for the pregnancy hormone that is
released in a woman's urine or detected
in a woman's urine when she is pregnant
what HCG does when it is injected by a
man is it mimics doesn't increase but
mimics a hormone called LH or
luteinizing hormone and that is a
hormone that is generally in a healthy
male secreted by the pituitary gland the
anterior pituitary in the front and is
secreted into the bloodstream it goes
down to the testicles and it works on
the interstitial ltic cells to stimulate
production of testosterone in the
process it also helps to maintain
testicular function and that
testosterone production and
intracellular aromatization or
conversion into estrad helps the CI
cells in the testes produce sperm that's
a process called
spermatogenesis for all of this to occur
we have to have two things present we
have to have good function fun ltic
cells and good functional CI cells
here's the problem when we make a
diagnosis and we always diagnose our
patients prior to prescribing
testosterone most people do not and
that's that's a problem because low
testosterone is not a diagnosis low
testosterone is a sign it is something
you can see on a piece of paper on a lab
report low testosterone is associated
with symptoms so you have the sign and
then you have the associated symptoms
neither is a diagnosis a medical
diagnosis is something that could be
pinpoint as to why it occurred what is
the ideology or the cause behind it so
when we diagnose a man who suffers from
low testosterone like symptoms we look
at the chain of command of the
luteinizing hormone from the pituitary
and the signaling agent that goes to the
testes and we try to figure out where
this chain broke or where it failed in a
male who is diagnosed with what we call
testicular hypo function slash primary
hypogonadism his testes or his cells
have failed they are essentially either
dying or they are dead already in
someone with secondary hypogonadism the
pituitary is failing to send a signal
down to the testes so if you are
secondary and that pituitary signal is
deficient giving you a mimetic like HCG
which mimics luteinizing hormone while
it is suppressive to the pituitary will
in fact stimulate the LX cells to
continue working this does a number of
things that are wonderful for some guys
it may help to preserve testicular
function and prevent mild testicular
atrophy which is a fancy word for
shrinkage of the testicles it is purely
cosmetic there's no risk factors
associated but some guys don't like the
Cosmetic effect so they complain of it
and I will state that probably maybe 20
or 25% of all patients on testrone ever
report experiencing this so it is not as
common as you
think and the second thing is because
we're stimulating very slight endogenous
testosterone production from the LX
cells the CI cells benefit by
maintaining some level of
spermatogenesis so this is very nice for
guys who are one diagnosed with
secondary hypogonadism and two still
want to maintain um some level of
fertility in the future coupled with
prevention of thetic atrophy where does
this not apply is for guys who are a
definitively strong primary hypogonadal
candidate where their testicular
function is completely diminished
mimicking luteinizing hormone in other
Iz nonfunctional testes is completely
moot it is a waste of money and it
you're just buying expensive water at
that point so I I apologize for the
mildly complex explanation but HCG is
not a one-size fits-all it has to First
be uh looked at from a diagnostic
standpoint and does it fit into the
equation or not and this requires
someone who understands the mechanism of
the hbta and and why someone's
production actually failed